Finding Aid for Bentley Historical Library publications, 1935-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bentley Historical Library publications 1935-2012
Bentley Historical Library.
0052 Bimu C445 2
The Bentley Historical Library (BHL) houses the Michigan Historical collections, which documents the history of Michigan; and the University Archives and Records Program, which maintains the historical records of the University of Michigan. Founded in 1935 as the Michigan Historical Collections, directors of the library include Lewis G. Vander Velde, F. Clever Bald, Robert M. Warner and Francis X. Blouin, Jr. The publications include annual reports, bulletins, bibliographies, newsletters, and books produced by the BHL using its holdings
3.7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donor No. 1991.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The origins of the Bentley Historical Library (BHL) can be traced to two related projects initiated in the 1930s at the University of Michigan. In early 1934, Professor Lewis G. Vander Velde successfully applied for a $700 grant to locate and collect primary source material relating to the history of Michigan. Approximately a year later, in November 1935, University of Michigan President Alexander Ruthven appointed a Committee on University Archives and authorized it to gather together the university's historical records. Vander Velde served as secretary to this committee. Space was set aside in the William L. Clements Library for both projects, and Vander Velde, with the assistance of a single graduate student, undertook both projects. In June 1938, the two enterprises moved into three rooms of the newly completed Rackham Building. That same year the Regents named the endeavor the Michigan Historical Collections (MHC). In 1973, the library moved from its quarters in the Rackham Building into the newly completed Bentley Historical Library on the university's north campus. For the first time, the MHC had for a home a facility designed and built for the processing and use of the manuscript and archival materials that it had been collecting for nearly forty years.
In the formative years of the MHC, Vander Velde supervised a surprisingly large staff. Funds from the Works Progress Administration made possible the hiring of a large number of special assistants. In 1939, twenty individuals were packing, processing, and cleaning records as they were collected. Although World War II quickly drained away the funds used to pay these many employees, a great deal of work was accomplished and Vander Velde retained some professional assistance. In 1938 or 1939, Vander Velde hired a full-time assistant primarily to collect historical records. In 1951, he added a permanent printed works librarian to the staff.
In 1947, Vander Velde was appointed chair of the university's history department. To lighten his administrative burden at the MHC, F. Clever Bald was appointed to the newly created post, assistant director. Vander Velde retained the title of director of the MHC until 1960, when he retired and was succeeded by Bald. In 1966 Bald retired and was succeeded by Robert M. Warner. In 1980, Warner resigned as director to become head of the National Archives. Richard Doolen served as acting director until 1981 when Francis X. Blouin, Jr. became the fourth director of the BHL. Blouin would serve as director until 2013.
In 1979, a separate program for the administration of the university archives was formally established. The University Archives and Records Program (UARP) became a separate division alongside the MHC, which continued to focus on documenting the state of Michigan. Reference services and conservation were reconfigured as divisions providing the current structure of four divisions (MHC, UARP, Reference and Access, and Preservation and Conservation) under the broader designation of the Bentley Historical Library (BHL). A fifth division, Digital Curation was added to the BHL in April 2011 to handle the preservation and archiving of digital records.
Issued in 2004 on the occasion of the dedication of an addition to its building The Bentley Historical Library Its History and Purpose provides a more complete history of the Bentley Historical Library. There is further detail about the Bentley and its functions on its home page at http://bentley.umich.edu.
The PUBLICATIONS (3.7 linear feet) are divided into two series: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications.
The Unit Publications series contains complete runs of the Bentley Historical Library publications. These include annual reports, 1935-2012 (except for 1989-1990 and 1997-2004, when no annual reports were published). The Unit Publications series also includes brochures, calendars, exhibit programs and manuals such as the University Archives and Records Program Records Policy and Procedures Manual. There is a complete run of topical resource bibliographies including the Bibliographic Series (No. 1-11) dating from 1973 to 1988 and the Guide Series written starting in 1996. In 2001 a guide to holdings relating to Detroit was published. The Unit Publications series includes a comprehensive collection of bibliographies such as the Guide to Manuscripts in the Bentley Historical Library published in 1976 and a bibliography of works derived using the holdings in the Bentley Historical Library, 1935-2010, issued as the Bentley celebrated its 75th anniversary in 2010. The Bulletin Series is a series of booklets largely written on Michigan or University of Michigan topics using Bentley Library collections and record groups as source material. This series began in 1947 and continues to the present.
The Unit Publications series contains monographs published by or in conjunction with the Bentley Historical Library. This eclectic subseries includes a biography of Ann Allen written by Russell Bidlack, a history of the Detroit observatory by Patricia Whitesell, and an updated edition of Howard Peckham's history of the University of Michigan. There have been two newsletters published by the unit, the Michigan Historical Collection Gazette published from 1967 to 1988 and the Bentley Historical Library which began publication in 1989 and continues to the present.
The Sub-Unit Publications series contains undated brochures from the Friends of the Bentley Historical Library.
Subjects:
Michigan Historical Collections.; Bentley Historical Library.
Genre Terms:
Annual reports.; Newsletters.; Bibliographies.; Bulletins.; Brochures.; Calendars.; Manuals.; Monographs.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  - Annual Reports
    - 1935-2012, 41 folders (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - Guide to Manuscripts in the Bentley Historical Library, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Guide to the Microfilm Edition of Temperance and Prohibition Papers 1977 (Box 1)
    - Guide to the Microfilm Edition of the Detroit Urban League Records, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Guide to the Archives of the University of Michigan, January 1992 revised edition (Box 1)
    - Sources for the Study of Migration and Ethnicity: A Guide to Manuscripts in Finland, Ireland, Poland, The Netherlands and the State of Michigan, 1979 (Box 1)
    - 75 Years of Scholarship: A Bibliography of Works Derived from the Holdings of the Michigan Historical Collections and the University Archives in the Bentley Historical Library, 1935-2010 2010 (Box 2)
  - Bibliographical Series (No. 1-11)
    - No. 1, Resources on the History of Pacifism and Conscientious Objection in the Michigan Historical Collections 1973, 1976 revised edition (Box 2)
    - No. 2, Resources on Conservation and Natural Resources in the Michigan Historical Collections 1970 (Box 2)
    - No. 3, Resources on the Protestant Episcopal Church in Michigan 1970 (Box 2)
    - No. 4, Resources on Temperance and Prohibition in the Michigan Historical Collections 1974 (Box 2)
    - No. 5, Unpublished Resources on the History of Mass Communications in the Michigan Historical Collections 1975 (Box 2)
    - No. 6, Athletics, Sports, and Games: A Bibliography of Resources in the Michigan Historical Collections 1979 (Box 2)
    - No. 7, Native Americans in Michigan: A Bibliography of Resources in the Michigan Historical Collections 1979 (Box 2)
    - No. 8, The Clergy in Michigan: A Bibliography of Resources in the Michigan Historical Collections 1980 (Box 2)
    - No. 9, The Underground Press in Michigan: A Bibliography of Resources in the Michigan Historical Collections 1982 (Box 2)
    - No. 10, American-Philippine Relations: A Bibliography of Resources in the Michigan Historical Collections 1982 (Box 2)
    - No. 11, American Intervention in Northern Russia 1918-1919 The Polar Bear Expedition: A Guide to the Resources in the Michigan Historical Collections, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Guide Series
    - No. 1, The Board of Regents of the University of Michigan: A Guide to the Resources in the Bentley Historical Library 1996 (Box 2)
    - No. 2, Poliomyelitis and the Salk Vaccine: A Guide to the Resources in the Bentley Historical Library, 1996. (Box 2)
    - No. 3, Detroit: A Guide to the Resources in the Bentley Historical Library September 2001 (Box 2)
  - Bookmarks
    - "Michigan Modernism: Architecture and Archives at the University of Michigan," undated (Box 2)
    - "Michigan Union Ornament for Fireplace Designed by Pond and Pond, 1917" undated (Box 2)
  - Brochures
    - General 1936-2007, undated (Box 2)
    - The Bentley Historical Library at the University of Michigan: What Is It? undated (Box 2)
    - Immigration Sources Project undated (Box 2)
    - The Bentley Historical Library in the Electronic Environment, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Preparing for the Future: The Fiftieth Anniversary Fund and Commemorative Plaque, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Teaching in the Archives, circa 2005 (Box 2)
    - Teaching with Research Collections Postdoctoral Fellowship Program, circa 2007 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins
    - Bulletin Index (Box 2)
    - No. 1 Early Dutch Settlement in Michigan as Revealed by Selections from Manuscripts in the Michigan Historical Collections, 1947 (Box 2)
    - No. 2, Gabriel Richard the First Vice-President of the University of Michigan, 1948 includes reissued 1967 copy, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - No. 3 Michigan Historical Collections of the University of Michigan, 1948 includes revised edition 1956, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - No. 4 Promise and Performance: The Political Record of a Michigan Governor, Chase Salmon Osborn, reissued 1960 (Box 2)
    - No. 5 President as Poet: A Note on the life of Henry Philip Tappan, D.D. 1952 (Box 2)
    - No. 6 The Staebler Papers, 1953 includes supplement Last Days of the Toledo Steamer, 1954 (Box 2)
    - No. 7 Michigan: Pioneer in Education, 1955 (Box 2)
    - No. 8 Andrew Dickson White, Teacher of History, 1958 (Box 2)
    - No. 9 Michigan Men in the Civil War, 1959 includes 1960, 1966 supplements (see also no. 27) (Box 2)
    - No. 10 Chase Salmon Osborn, 1860-1949, 1960 (Box 2)
    - No. 11, The Michigan Historical Collections: the Vander Velde Years, Twenty-Five Years of Leadership, 1961 (Box 2)
    - No. 12 John Allen and the Founding of Ann Arbor, 1962 (Box 2)
    - No. 13 The Michigan Historical Collections of the University of Michigan, undated (Box 2)
    - No. 14 Michigan's Polar Bears: The American Expedition to North Russia, 1918-1919, 1965 (Box 2)
    - No. 15 John Monteith, First President of the University of Michigan, 1967 (Box 2)
    - No. 16 Notes on a Tour: Annotations to a Pictorial Exhibit Celebrating the Sesquicentennial of the University of Michigan, 1967 (Box 2)
    - No. 17 Frank Murphy in World War I, 1968 (Box 2)
    - No. 18 Toward Camelot: The Admission of Women to the University of Michigan, 1970 (Box 2)
    - No. 19 Balita Mula Maynila (News from Manila), 1971 (Box 2)
    - No. 20 A Brief History of the Detroit Urban League and Description of the League's Papers in the Michigan Historical Collections, 1971 (Box 2)
    - No. 21 James Kerr Pollack: His Life and Letters, 1972 (Box 2)
    - No. 22 History of the Michigan Historical Collections, 1974 (Box 2)
    - No. 23 Local History is Alive and Well: An Address Given on the Occasion of the Dedication of the Bentley Historical Library, 1974 (Box 2)
    - No. 24 Wilber M. Brucker, 1894-1968, 1974 (Box 2)
    - No. 25 Arthur H. Vandenberg: His Career and Legacy, 1975 (Box 2)
    - No. 26 The Finns in the United States: The Project on Finnish Immigration of the Michigan Historical Collections, 1976 (Box 2)
    - No. 27 Michigan Men in the Civil War, 1977 (Box 2)
    - No. 28 The Anatomy of a Speech: Lyndon Johnson's Great Society Address, 1978 (Box 2)
    - No. 29 A Furniture Family: The Slighs of Michigan, 1980 (Box 2)
    - No. 30 Telltale Photographs: The Stoner Railroad Collection, 1981 (Box 2)
    - No. 31 The Early Years of the University of Michigan Medical School: The Upjohn Family Experience, 1982 (Box 2)
    - No. 32 An Enduring Gift: The Bentley Historical Library, Keeper of Michigan History, 1983 (Box 2)
    - No. 33 The History and Purpose of the Michigan Historical Collections, 1983 (Box 2)
    - No. 34 Biography of an Endowment: The Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund at the University of Michigan, 1985 (Box 2)
    - No. 35 Neil Staebler: His Career and Legacy, 1987 (Box 2)
    - No. 36 Some Centennials of the American of the American Constitution and Others, 1987 (Box 2)
    - No. 37 The Evolving Role of the President's Wife at the University of Michigan: A Special Tea with Anne Hatcher, Sally Fleming, and Vivian Shapiro, 1989 (Box 2)
    - No. 38 John Harris Forster: Field Notes of a Surveyor in Panama and California, 1989 (Box 2)
    - No. 39 The University of Michigan On the Air: the Audio-Visual Education Center, the Television Center, and Michigan Media, 1992 (Box 3)
    - No. 40 Detroit and the Great Migration, 1916-1919, 1993 (Box 3)
    - No. 41 The Governors of Michigan, 1835-1991 A Brief Guide to Papers of Governors of the State of Michigan Held by the Bentley Historical Library, 1994 (see also number 58) (Box 3)
    - No. 42 Michigan on the March: the University of Michigan in World War II, 1995 (Box 3)
    - No. 43 Civil Rights and the Michigan Constitution of 1963, 1996 (Box 3)
    - No. 44 Thought and Action: John Dewey at the University of Michigan, 1998 (Box 3)
    - No. 45 Social Science in the Public Interest: A Fiftieth --Year History of the Institute for Social Research, 1998 (Box 3)
    - No. 46 Pleasant Walks and Drives about Ann Arbor, 1999 (Box 3)
    - No. 47 Frost-Bite & Frost-Bark: Robert Frost at Michigan, 1999 (Box 3)
    - No. 48 Archives, Documentation, and the Institutions of Society Memory, August 2000 (Box 3)
    - No. 49 Women's Voices: Early Years at the University of Michigan, October 2000 (misnumbered as No. 47) (Box 3)
    - No. 50 Not Perfect, But Just Right: A Tour of the Conservation Area, April 2004 (Box 3)
    - No. 51 John Sinclair and the Culture of the Sixties, October 2004 (Box 3)
    - No. 52 The University of Michigan and China: 1845-2006, April 2006 (Box 3)
    - No. 53 A Presidential Library Comes to Ann Arbor, January 2007 (Box 3)
    - No. 54 The University of Michigan and China: 1845-2008, September 2007 (Box 3)
    - No. 55 A Century of Connectivity at the University of Michigan, December 2007 (Box 3)
    - No. 54, revised The University of Michigan and China: 1845-2010, June 2010 (Box 3)
    - No. 56 A Discourse, Delivered by Henry P. Tappan, D.D. at Ann Arbor Michigan on the Occasion of His Inauguration as Chancellor of the University of Michigan, December 21st 1852, August 2010 (Box 3)
    - No. 57 Documenting the Arts at the Bentley Historical Library, September 2010 (Box 3)
    - No. 58 The Governors of Michigan, 1835-2011 A Brief Guide to Papers of Governors of the State of Michigan Held by the Bentley Historical Library, 2013 (Box 3)
  - Calendars
    - A Book of Days: 150 Years of Student Life at Michigan 1987 (Box 3)
  - Cookbooks
    - The Best of the Bentley: Tea Time Treasures, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Disaster Plans
    - Disaster Plan for the Bentley Library 1977 (Box 3)
  - Exhibits
    - Exhibit Flyers 1967-2008 (Box 3)
    - Michigan: Promise and Performance, 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - Native Peoples in Transition, Michigan Indians in the Nineteenth Century: An Exhibit at the Bentley Historical Library in Celebration of the Second European Conference on Archives 1989 (Box 3)
  - Flyers
    - General circa 1950-2010, undated (Box 3)
    - The Making of Ann Arbor, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Travel and Research Grants: Mark C. Stevens Fellowship & Bordin/Gillette Fellowship, undated (Box 3)
  - Guides (see also Bibliographies)
    - Guide to the Use of the Bentley Historical Library, 1979, 1999, 2004, 2011 (Box 3)
    - Guide to the Works of Art in Bentley Library Public Areas 1976 (Box 3)
  - Histories
    - The Bentley Historical Library: Its History and Purpose, issued on the occasion of the dedication of the addition to the building October, 2004, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Holiday Cards (sent)
    - Cards undated (Box 3)
  - Manuals
    - Records Policy and Procedures Manual, University Archives and Records Program, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Memorials
    - Earl D. Babst A Good Friend of History, 1967 (Box 3)
    - F. Clever Bald 1897-1970, circa 1970 (Box 3)
  - Monographs
    - Ann Arbor's First Lady: Events in the Life of Ann I. Allen, 1998 (Box 3)
    - A Creation of His Own: Tappan's Detroit Observatory, 1998 (Box 3)
    - The Making of the University of Michigan, 1817-1992 175th Anniversary Edition edited and updated, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Intellectual Life on the Michigan Frontier: the Libraries of Gabriel Richard and John Monteith, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Explorations in its Social History, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Pictorial History of Ann Arbor, 1824-1974, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Aspirations of Excellence: Alexander Jackson Davis and the First Campus Plan for the University of Michigan, 1838, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Albert Kahn and his Family in Peace and War, 2006-2008 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Memories: Student Voices and Images, 1856-1935, 2005 (Box 4)
    - A Series of Firsts: Women in Michigan Science and Engineering, 1940-1985 2011 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters
    - The Bentley Historical Library, 1989-2012, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Michigan Historical Collections Gazette, 1967-1988, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Programs
    - Groundbreaking and Dedication Programs 1972-1977, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Reports
    - A Decade of Sponsored Research: The Research Fellowship Program for Study of Modern Archives 1994 (Box 4)
    - Electronic Records Research and Development: Final Report of the 1996 Conference Held at the University of Michigan, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Uses of Communication to Document an Academic Community: Final Report to the National Historical Publications and Records Commission, Grant no. 91-113, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Topical Publications
    - 50th Anniversary 1985 (Box 4)
    - 75th Anniversary 2010 (Box 4)
    - American Archives in the Eyes of Chinese Young Archivists: Reports in Commemoration of the 12th Anniversary of SAAC-Bentley Archival Exchange Program, 2011 (Box 4)
    - History of the University of Michigan's President's House (in conjunction with the History and Traditions Committee) 1996 (Box 4)
    - International Conference on Archives (ICA) Second European Conference on Archives 1989 (Box 4)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  - Friends of the Michigan Historical Collections / Bentley Historical Library
    - Brochures undated (Box 4)